<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two petitions presented to the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled: the one, the humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the City of London in Common-Councell assembled: the other, the humble petition of the field officers, captaines, and their commission-officers of the trained-bands of the City of London and liberties thereof. With the answers of both Houses to the said petitions.</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E451_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203856</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863656</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863656</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95474)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E451[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two petitions presented to the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled: the one, the humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the City of London in Common-Councell assembled: the other, the humble petition of the field officers, captaines, and their commission-officers of the trained-bands of the City of London and liberties thereof. With the answers of both Houses to the said petitions.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Cotes, printer to the Honourable City of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>July 5. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The replies are dated 5 July 1648.</note>
                  <note>"In favor of a personal treaty with the King and for the strengthening of the London militia"  Thomason.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161920:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO PETITIONS <hi>PRESENTED</hi> To the Right Honourable THE LORDS and COMMONS in Parliament Aſſembled: The One, The humble Petition of the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons of the City of <hi>London</hi> IN <hi>Common-Councell aſſembled:</hi> The Other, The humble Petition of the Field Officers, Captaines, and their Commiſſion-Officers OF THE <hi>TRAINED-BANDS</hi> of the City of <hi>London</hi> and Liberties thereof.</p>
            <p>With the Anſwers of both Houſes to the ſaid Petitions.</p>
            <p>Printed by RICHARD COTES, Printer to the Honourable City of <hi>London,</hi> July 5. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:161920:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161920:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE The Commons IN THE High Court of Parliament aſſembled:</hi> The humble Petition of the Lord Major, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Commons of the City of London, in Common-councell aſſembled</head>
            <opener>SHEVVETH,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT your Petitioners ſitting in Common-Councell upon the weighty Affairs of the City, had preſented unto them by divers Field-Officers, Captaines, and their Commiſſion-Officers of the Trained-Bands of the City of <hi>London</hi> and Liberties
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161920:3"/> thereof, the Petition hereunto annexed; which being openly read, and ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of, they apprehend that the ſame is of great concernment, worthy due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, tending to the Honour and ſafety of the King, and preſervation of the Parliament, and the ſettlement of the peace and welfare of the City and Kingdom; and they (concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the Petitioners therein) have thought fit to preſent the ſame to this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe; And they humbly pray your Honours to take the ſame into your ſerious conſideration; And to doe therein as in your grave Wiſdoms you ſhall ſee fit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And they ſhall pray, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:161920:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honourable THE LORDS Aſſembled in Parliament.</hi> The humble Petition of the Field-Officers, Captains and their Commiſſion-Officers of the Trained-bands of the City of <hi>London</hi> and Liberties thereof,</head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat out of the deep ſenſe of the ſad Miſeries that lie upon theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the onely viſible remedy whereof (under God) we conceive to be a Perſonall Treatie with his Majeſtie; Which happy worke we hear is like to be retarded, if not fruſtrated, by feares and jealouſies ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, if it ſhould be here in <hi>London,</hi> (which is ſo much deſired,) That in ſtead of ſetling
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161920:4"/> Peace, it might involve us all in blood, by Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults that might be raiſed by Perſons driving on their own Deſignes and Intereſts: VVe think our ſelves bound in duty, for promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſo deſirable a VVork, ſo much as in us lieth, to offer our ſervice with our lives and fortunes to the utmoſt, to defend His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Royall perſon, and this Parliament from all violence whatſoever, that they may meet and Treat with freedom, honour, and ſafety, according to the ancient fundamentall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of this Kingdom; and, That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall by Tumults, Mutinies, Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections or otherwiſe, interrupt or force the Honour, Freedom, and Safety of the King or Parliament; VVe, and all under our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ſhall be ready as One man to live and die in defence of the King and Parliament, according to our Covenant.</p>
            <p n="1">I. VVherefore we humbly pray, That for our enablement thereunto, the Militia of the City of <hi>London</hi> and adjacent parts may be ſetled in one Committee: And if
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161920:4"/> in your VViſdoms you ſhall think fit, to joyn ſome perſons of the Parts adjacent to the Grand Committee, they may be ſuch as have no places of Profit which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the continuance of the VVarr, and our troubles; or have ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſaffected to the ends of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the King may be brought to <hi>London</hi> with freedom, honour, and ſafety, to Treat with His Parliament, for the ſetling of a ſafe and wel-grounded Peace.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That the Militia may have power to raiſe Horſe, if need be, for the defence of the King, Parliament, and City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And we ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:161920:5"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Mercurii, 5. Julii, 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Lords have commanded me to let you know, That they have conſidered of the Petitions this day tendred by you unto them. They had of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves made ſome progreſs in thoſe things mentioned therein; and they doe now declare unto you, That they have thought fit to grant your deſires in all the particulars contained in the Petitions; in confidence, That the City of <hi>London</hi> will be care<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull to make good their great engagement now made for the preſerving and ſecuring of His Majeſties Perſon and the Parliament from Tumults, Mutinies, Inſurrections, or other Diſorders that may interrupt the Honour, Freedom, and Safety of the King or Parliament; And they cannot doubt, but, That they will ſtill adhere to live and die in defence of the King and Parliament according to their Covenant.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Io. Brown Cler. Parliamentorum.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_petition">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Mercurii 5. Iulii, 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>The Houſe being informed that the Sheriffs, divers Aldermen and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the City of <hi>London</hi> were at door, they were called in, and after a ſhort preamble made by Sheriff <hi>Byde,</hi> they preſented two Petitions; the one enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, The humble Petition of the Field-Officers, Captaines, and their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion Officers of the trained Bands of the city of <hi>London</hi> and liberties thereof, which they ſaid was brought to them Yeſterday as they ſate in Common-councell; the other from themſelves, entituled, The humble Petition of the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons of the city of <hi>London</hi> in Common-councell; which after the Petitioners were withdrawn were read.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ordered,</hi>
               <lb/> That on Friday next, the debate touching the Petitions now preſented, be again taken into conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ordered,</hi>
               <lb/> That it be referred to the Committee to confer with the Common-councell of the city of <hi>London,</hi> and ſuch as they ſhall appoint, and with the Commanders of the Souldiers in <hi>London,</hi> concerning their engagement for the ſafety of the King and Parliament during the intended Treatie, and touching the manner of the ſecurity.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners being again called in, Mr. Speaker by command of the Houſe gave them this anſwer;</p>
            <p>The Houſe has read your Petition, and the Petition annexed; And they have agreed to the joyning the Militia's.</p>
            <p>The other matters contained in the Petition, are of great concernement, and have taken up much debate, and they have appointed another day to take up the ſaid debate; and have alſo appointed a Committee to confer with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-councell of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and ſuch as they ſhall appoint; and with the Commanders of the Souldiers in <hi>London</hi> about the ſame; wherewith the Houſe deſires you to acquaint the Lord Maior, that a Common-councell may be called to morrow at two of the clock in the afternoon, for a conference thereupon accordingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
